<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: lvmcache | Deku Scrub]]></title>
  <link href="//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/categories/lvmcache/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//"/>
  <updated>2014-06-19T00:31:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ricky Ayoub]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 12: Kernel Upgrading and Reinstallation]]></title>
    <link href="//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/2014/06/06/day-12-kernel-upgrading-and-reinstallation/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-06T19:32:48-04:00</updated>
    <id>//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/2014/06/06/day-12-kernel-upgrading-and-reinstallation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The toolset <code>lvmcache</code> is special in that it isn&rsquo;t supported in the default kernel that ships with Fedora 20. My RHEL7 machines (and partition on my laptop) have no issues using it, but it would be most useful to have functioning on my laptop. After a lot of researching I learned that it eventually boiled down to the version of the linux kernel that I was using.</p>

<p><code>
uname -r
</code></p>

<p>The above command reports information about the kernel. I was running 3.11, which does not have <a href="https://github.com/mingzhao/dm-cache">dm-cache</a> support. The README lists instructions on how to compile the kernel module, but I had mixed results. My knowledge of how a kernel is actually compiled is severly limited given my previous userland background, but that didn&rsquo;t mean that I wasn&rsquo;t ready to give it my all. The short explanation is that it may not have been as simple as the instructions made it out to be. The long explanation is that I spent a long time downloading various kernel sources and headers  trying to recompile and add this module to the kernel.</p>

<p>The process is all very official and streamlined, but it still gave me some issues. For that reason, I am choosing <em>not</em> to include the instructions here, for fear that someone else will build upon my mistakes. After I finally seemed to have everything functioning, I didn&rsquo;t actually know how to &ldquo;activate&rdquo; it. When flashing kernels on Android, it&rsquo;s always fairly obvious. I mean, you usually just go to recovery and literally flash it. There&rsquo;s no concept of multiple kernels or anything.</p>

<p><code>
sudo yum update kernel
</code></p>

<p>It should be noted here that, prior to deciding to jump in and compile my own kernel, I had tried the simple above command. When I first typed it, I thought I was an idiot, it couldn&rsquo;t be so simple. Once it actually started to download and install kernel 3.14 though, I then felt very satisfied. Upon rebooting though, the kernel still wasn&rsquo;t activated. Well, to get back to my own compiled kernel, the case was the same for that. Neither the updated kernel from yum nor my own custom kernel seemed to be activated.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure if I missed something along the lines, and I was getting increasingly frustrated, so I performed a reinstall of Fedora 20. As you know, my home directory is on another partition, so all of my data and preferences were still intact. Still though, my kernel refused to update. Then it hit me, and things started to click into place. The whole manner in which my system functions is it loads a kernel into ram from a /boot physical partition selected via grub, and this kernel then mounts and loads the filesystem and all its contents.</p>

<p>Well, as it turned out that was an oversimplication. It would seem that the grub bootloader entries actually contain information about the kernel that is being used at boot. Unlike the Android model where you can flash and only use one at a time, it would seem the kernels are almost hot swappable via grub. I should have expected such functionality.</p>

<p><code>
grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub/grub.cfg
</code></p>

<p>So as it turned out, getting grub to re-run the OS scanner and reconfigure itself allowed it to pick up both kernels, and 3.11 and 3.14 are both selectable at boot time. Such fine grained control should have been expected. I&rsquo;m a little surprised that I had never come across this in any of my kernel building tutorials, but I should probably blame myself for not having ran a real multi-boot linux machine in a long time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 11: Triple Threat]]></title>
    <link href="//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/2014/06/05/day-11-triple-threat/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T19:32:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/2014/06/05/day-11-triple-threat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Much of my job consists of taking my computers&hellip; and destroying them. Well, I&rsquo;m not supposed to be destroying them, and I&rsquo;m not necessarily trying to either, but usually in testing LVM I manage to find one way or another to make the machines unbootable. Thankfully, due to the wealth of LVM information out there, more often than not I am capable of fixing the problems that develop on my laptop, but for the desktops it&rsquo;s usually just less effort to reformat them and try something different.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/computer_problems.png">http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/computer_problems.png</a>"></p>

<p>I was going to put in that <a href="http://xkcd.com/349/">other xkcd</a> relating to computer problems, but this one seems more appropriate.</p>

<p>Now don&rsquo;t get me wrong, breaking the computers isn&rsquo;t necessarily <em>bad</em>. The actual problem is the fact that usually they break because of something that <em>I</em> do to them that&rsquo;s out of line. But then I learn so even that isn&rsquo;t a lose-lose situation. In reality, if I could find something that the user would expect to work according to the documentation that consistently (this being the key word here) breaks the machine, then I can create a bugzilla report from that.</p>

<p>So today&rsquo;s big news was that I had all three computers down, and was gong back and forth between them all frantically trying to fix them. For the laptop that means making sure I can still boot to my fedora install–- this usually means fixing it from the rhel7 release candidate dual boot. For the other two computers, it&rsquo;s reformatting them and deciding on a new order / seeing what exactly went wrong during the latest install. Although Red Hat has a network boot system with a bunch of system installers on it, I usually find it easier to use my usb with rhel7 on it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m pretty picky with bugs, but I am surprised by how it can sometimes be very simple to break the boot order. That being said, I am practically playing with fire here with some of the commands that I run.</p>

<p><code>
mkfs.ext4 /dev/mapper/vg-thinpool
</code></p>

<p>The above command will format the thinpool and at first I was surprised that it worked, but in retrospect I don&rsquo;t know how it could be prevented. Upon running it my thin volumes that were within that pool seemed totally broken (and I can&rsquo;t say that I didn&rsquo;t expect them to be.)</p>

<p>Another caveat that frequently and still catches me is when I&rsquo;m playing around with a ramdisk via loop back device as discussed a few posts ago. If one reboots without running <code>vgreduce</code> to remove the loopback device from the volume group, chaos usually ensues.</p>

<p>When it&rsquo;s all said and done though, hopefully I can find some combination that people haven&rsquo;t accounted for that will destroy the systems. And until then, hopefully I can understand how and why the machine are actually breaking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 08: Enter the Cache]]></title>
    <link href="//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/2014/06/02/day-08-enter-the-cache/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T18:24:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>//vgmoose.github.io/deku-scrub/blag//blog/2014/06/02/day-08-enter-the-cache</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Logical volumes are very unique in the sense that you can inject some higher level logic into something as low level as the bytes on your disk. Flash disks are very fast, but large ones are also still very expensive. This obviously creates an interesting problem for server maintainers, as ideally large amount of content would be served as fast as possible which would require the best of both worlds.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/deku-scrub/blag/images/cash.gif"></p>

<p>Not.. that kind of cash. Ha. HA HA. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dm-cache">dm-cache</a> was a proprosed kernel module solution to allow quick access to frequently used blocks from a large slow disk using a quick fast disk. As of <a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/device-mapper/cache.txt">April 28, 2013</a> it is now officially a part of the Linux kernel. The Wiki article does a better job of explaining, as usual, but dm-cache helps speed up a slow device by storing only the modified blocks to the fast device and marking the slow device as dirty, allowing full reads and writes to occur solely off the cache. For this reason, it is recommended that the caching device be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_RAID_levels#RAID_1">mirrored</a>.</p>

<p>LVM cache, from my understanding, provides an easy approach to allow the user to configure this through LVM by making use of the dm-cache module. At its heart, lvmcache requires an original, large and slow logical volume, and then a smaller but fast logical volume. A third logical volume is also utilized for metadata storage, not unlike how a thinpool stores its metadata.</p>

<p>An odd tidbit about lvmcache, though, is that the logical volumes that are utilized must all be within the same volume group. To review, a physical volume (like an actual primary partition of a device or another device entirely) can only be within one volume group at a time, and the volume group provides an abstraction over those physical devices to the logical volumes. Or at least that&rsquo;s what I thought.</p>

<p><code>
lvcreate -n isolated -L 10G volume_group /dev/sdb1
</code></p>

<p>Yeah, so apparently you can pass a physical volume to the logical volume creation command and it will ensure that all writes go to that device. At least, that&rsquo;s my understanding of it. I&rsquo;m not entirely sure how you&rsquo;d enforce say, a 10G logical volume, if you tied it to a 4G device, and I really don&rsquo;t enjoy how it breaches the abstraction provided by the volume group.</p>

<p>Addtionally I can&rsquo;t seem to be able to figure out just <em>where</em> these devices are listed (they aren&rsquo;t listed in <code>lvdisplay</code>). The process can also be simplified by using tags, which I do know how to display.</p>

<p><code>
lvs -o+tags
</code></p>

<p>But unfortunately, I don&rsquo;t know much else about them. I believe though that they provide some abstraction that was desired previously with the bypassing of the volume group. <a href="http://rwmj.wordpress.com/2014/05/30/lvm-cache-contd-tip-using-tags/">Here is more information</a> on that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
